Hello, everyone, and welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And my name is Catherine.
我是Catherine。
So Marco, today we're talking about rent and housing.
那么Marco，今天我们聊聊租金和住房。
Right.
没错。
We're actually going to be moving.
我们其实要搬家了。
We're going to be going to a new apartment or a new house.
我们要搬去一个新公寓或新房子。
And so we're going to look at all the words related to this because sometimes it can be
所以我们要看看所有相关的词汇，因为有时候这
a real hassle, right?
真的很麻烦，对吧？
It can be really difficult.
可能会非常困难。
Absolutely.
确实。
Well, you love moving, right?
嗯，你喜欢搬家，对吧？
You were telling me how much you love moving your stuff and negotiating a new lease.
你之前跟我说你有多喜欢搬东西和谈新租约。
Well, I like the negotiation of the lease, but not the moving aspect.
嗯，我喜欢谈租约，但不喜欢搬家那部分。
No, I don't think anyone likes moving.
不，我觉得没人喜欢搬家。
Actually, I do like it at times because then you can just throw away so many things that
其实，有时候我还挺喜欢的，因为你可以扔掉很多
you have no need for and you wouldn't throw away unless you moved.
你不需要的东西，而且除非搬家，否则你不会扔。
So let's go check out today's dialogue to find out what happens to the characters.
那我们来看看今天的对话，看看角色们发生了什么。
Okay, that's fine.
好的，没问题。
Bye.
再见。
What happened?
发生什么事了？
That's it.
就这样。
My lease is up.
我的租约到期了。
I have to move.
我得搬家。
What?
什么？
Why?
为什么？
Can't you renew it?
你不能续租吗？
The owner apparently is selling this place to make way for the construction of a parking
房东显然要卖掉这个地方，为建一个停车场
lot.
腾地方。
Well, I can help you pack.
嗯，我可以帮你打包。
We should start looking for a new place for you ASAP.
我们应该尽快开始给你找新地方。
I think I might move in with my parents for a couple of months until I can find something.
我想我可能会搬去和父母住几个月，直到找到合适的。
You know how hard it is to find a decent place around here.
你知道在这附近找个像样的地方有多难。
I'm going to have to put most of my stuff in storage for a while.
我得把大部分东西暂时存到仓库里。
Well, let me know if there's anything I can do to help out.
嗯，如果有什么我能帮忙的，告诉我。
Actually, would you mind looking after my pet tarantula and snake for a couple of weeks?
其实，你愿意帮我照看我的宠物狼蛛和蛇几周吗？
Sure.
当然。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So well, it's not much of a big deal.
所以嘛，这也不是什么大事。
I guess if you have your parents nearby, you can just move back in with your parents.
我想如果你父母在附近，你可以直接搬回去和他们住。
Easier said than done.
说起来容易做起来难。
True.
没错。
We'll get to that in a little bit, but let's take a look at the words that are used today
我们一会儿再谈这个，先看看今天在“语言要点”里用到的词。
in Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
Language Takeaway.
All right, so this first one is an important one because generally when you're looking
好的，第一个词很重要，因为通常你在找
for a house or an apartment, there are two things you can do.
房子或公寓时，有两种选择。
You can buy a house or you can lease a house or apartment.
你可以买房子，或者租房子或公寓。
So lease here, Marco.
所以这里的lease，Marco。
It's basically to rent, right?
基本上就是租，对吧？
It's a contract where you agree to pay a monthly or a quarterly fee for using that house or
这是一种合同，你同意每月或每季度支付费用来使用那栋房子或
apartment.
公寓。
So do you own your apartment or do you lease it?
那你的公寓是买的还是租的？
No, mine, I lease.
不，我的，我是租的。
I am not a homeowner yet.
我还没成为房主。
Right.
没错。
So owning a home is a lot more expensive at one kind of period where you have to just
所以拥有房子在某个阶段要贵得多，你得一次性
pay in and you have maybe a mortgage.
付清，或者可能有房贷。
But leasing is just a monthly fee, like you said.
但租就是每月付一次费用，就像你说的。
So in this case, they had to leave because their lease was expired.
所以在这个例子里，他们得搬走，因为租约到期了。
Exactly.
正是。
So you can, at the end of a lease, do one of two things.
所以在租约结束时，你可以做两件事之一。
You can stop and you can find a new apartment or you can renew your lease.
你可以停止并找新公寓，或者你可以续租。
All right.
好的。
And that's our next word.
那是我们的下一个词。
To renew your lease basically means to?
续租基本上意味着？
To continue.
继续。
And this is actually a good word because it can be used with any contract because really
这其实是个好词，因为它可以用在任何合同上，因为真的
a lease is a kind of contract.
租约就是一种合同。
And so I can say, I renewed my job contract.
所以我可以说我续签了工作合同。
Or maybe a magazine subscription.
或者可能是杂志订阅。
You renewed your magazine subscription.
你续订了杂志订阅。
It's a way of saying that you've committed to paying for the next six months or one year.
这是一种表示你承诺再付六个月或一年费用的方式。
Okay.
好的。
Well, and after that, as we said, the person decided to move in with the parents.
嗯，之后，就像我们说的，这个人决定搬去和父母住。
So move in.
所以搬进去。
Move in.
搬进去。
Well, we can say he moved his car.
嗯，我们可以说他移动了他的车。
He put it in a different place.
他把它放到了不同的地方。
But to move in is actually to change houses or to change apartments.
但搬进去实际上是换房子或换公寓。
And you're literally moving your things and you're moving your clothes and you're moving
你真的是在搬你的东西，搬你的衣服，搬
into a new home.
进一个新家。
So you're living in a new place.
所以你住在一个新地方。
So in this case, this person is going to live with the parents.
所以在这个例子里，这个人要搬去和父母住。
Move in.
搬进去。
All right.
好的。
And our next word is when you have to move, you have to pack.
我们的下一个词是，当你必须搬家时，你得打包。
Okay.
好的。
So you can pack a lot of things.
所以你可以打包很多东西。
In this case, you're packing a box with all of your belongings, your books and your pillows
在这个例子里，你在打包一个箱子，里面装着你所有的物品，你的书和枕头
and all that.
等等。
But you can also pack a suitcase or you can pack luggage.
但你也可以打包一个手提箱或打包行李。
So packing is putting things into something so that you can move them.
所以打包就是把东西放进某物里，这样你就可以移动它们。
So you can carry them or take them somewhere.
这样你就可以携带或带到某个地方。
Exactly.
正是。
So in this case, you have to pack your things, put them in boxes to take them to your new
所以在这个例子里，你得打包你的东西，放进箱子里，带到你的新
home.
家。
And our last word is an acronym when you said ASAP.
我们的最后一个词是一个缩写，你说了ASAP。
All right.
好的。
Snap, snap.
快点，快点。
Come on.
来吧。
ASAP, Marco.
ASAP，Marco。
ASAP.
ASAP。
Describe this for us quickly.
快给我们解释一下。
All right.
好的。
So ASAP is an acronym for as soon as possible.
所以ASAP是as soon as possible的缩写。
Okay.
好的。
So you often see this in the office on envelopes or emails.
所以你经常在办公室的信封或邮件上看到它。
So please respond ASAP.
所以请尽快回复。
This means please respond right away.
这意味着请马上回复。
As soon as you can.
尽快。
As soon as possible.
All right.
好的。
So five great words that we've just taken a look at.
所以我们刚刚看了五个很棒的词。
Let's listen to our dialogue again and we'll be right back.
让我们再听一遍我们的对话，我们马上回来。
Okay.
好的。
That's fine.
没问题。
Bye.
再见。
What happened?
发生什么事了？
That's it.
就这样了。
My lease is up.
我的租约到期了。
I have to move.
我得搬家了。
What?
什么？
Why?
为什么？
Can't you renew it?
你不能续租吗？
The owner apparently is selling this place to make way for the construction of a parking
房东显然要卖掉这个地方，为建一个停车场腾出空间。
lot.
停车场。
Well, I can help you pack.
嗯，我可以帮你打包。
We should start looking for a new place for you ASAP.
我们应该尽快开始给你找新地方。
I think I might move in with my parents for a couple of months until I can find something.
我想我可能会搬去和父母住几个月，直到找到合适的房子。
You know how hard it is to find a decent place around here.
你知道在这附近找个像样的地方有多难。
I'm going to have to put most of my stuff in storage for a while.
我得把大部分东西暂时存到仓库里。
Well, let me know if there's anything I can do to help out.
好吧，如果有什么我能帮忙的，就告诉我。
Actually, would you mind looking after my pet tarantula and snake for a couple of weeks?
其实，你愿意帮我照看我的宠物狼蛛和蛇几个星期吗？
Sure.
当然。
All right, we're back and we have a couple of different phrases for you.
好了，我们回来了，我们有几个不同的短语要教给你。
So let's look at those now in Fluency Builder.
现在让我们在流利度训练中看看这些。
Fluency Builder.
流利度训练。
Our first one's a little bit unusual.
第一个有点不寻常。
We heard the phrase, my lease is up.
我们听到了短语“my lease is up”。
So Marco, let's talk about this phrase, to be up.
所以Marco，我们来谈谈这个短语“to be up”。
All right.
好的。
So if something is up, as in this case, the lease, it means it's expired.
所以如果某件事“up”了，就像这里的租约，意思是它过期了。
It's finished.
结束了。
Right?
对吧？
So it's over.
所以就是结束了。
It's over.
结束了。
So it's like, our time is up.
就像我们的时间到了。
Right.
对。
If we have a meeting.
如果我们开会的话。
So that's all the time I have, time to go away.
所以这就是我所有的时间，该走了。
Time is up.
时间到了。
Very good.
很好。
So it's always related to time or maybe a contract, as in this case, or your lease is
所以它总是和时间或合同有关，就像这里，或者你的租约到期了。
up.
到期了。
So it means over or finished.
所以意思是结束或完成。
All right.
好的。
So moving on to our second phrase.
那么继续看我们的第二个短语。
To make way for.
让路给。
All right.
好的。
So this is a great one.
这个可太棒了。
This often makes me think of kings and queens in the old days.
这常常让我想起古代的国王和王后。
They say, make way for the king.
他们说，给国王让路。
So you have to get out of the way.
所以你得让开。
Yeah.
是的。
So they try to clear some space for them to move because there's too much stuff in the
所以他们试着清理出一些空间来活动，因为东西太多了。
way.
way. 方法。
And so in this case, the owner of the apartment with the guy was living in is trying to make
所以在这个案例中，公寓的房东，也就是那个男人住的地方的房东，正试图让……
some space or make way for a parking lot.
腾出一些空间，或者改建成停车场。
Right.
好的。
So he's basically going to sell the building or house and build a parking lot instead.
所以他基本上是要卖掉这栋楼或房子，然后改建成停车场。
So they are making way for the new parking lot.
所以他们正在为新停车场腾出空间。
They're clearing space.
他们在清理空间。
And this is actually really sad because my childhood home, they destroyed to make way
这真的很让人难过，因为我小时候住的那栋房子，他们把它拆了，为了给别的东西腾地方。
for a larger, ugly, big house.
一个更大、更丑、更大的房子。
Really?
真的吗？
Yeah.
是的。
It happens all the time.
这种事经常发生。
Now they're making way for malls and big buildings and all of our little houses are destroyed.
现在它们正被商场和高楼大厦取代，我们的小房子全被拆毁了。
And well, moving on to our last phrase, the person asked the friend if he would mind looking
好了，我们继续看最后一个短语。这个人问朋友是否介意帮忙照看一下。
after the pet snake and tarantula.
在宠物蛇和狼蛛之后。
I would mind.
我会介意的。
You don't like snakes or tarantulas?
你不喜欢蛇或狼蛛吗？
Well, I don't mind them as long as I don't live with them.
嗯，只要不和他们住一起，我倒是不介意。
So would you mind?
那么你介意吗？
This is a nice way to start a sentence if you want to ask for a favor, right?
这是一个很好的句子开头，如果你想请求帮助，对吧？
Exactly.
没错。
So here's an alternative.
那么这里有一个替代方案。
Hey, Marco, can you do this for me?
嘿，Marco，你能帮我做这个吗？
I could, maybe.
我或许可以。
I could say, Marco, would you mind doing this for me?
我可以说，Marco，你介意帮我做这个吗？
It's more polite.
这样更礼貌。
It is more polite and it's a little bit gentler.
这样更有礼貌，也更温和一些。
So it's a nice way of asking someone for a favor.
所以这是一种请人帮忙的礼貌方式。
Exactly.
没错。
And that's why this is funny because the favor is not like, would you mind watching my kitty?
这就是为什么这件事好笑，因为那个请求并不是“你能帮我照看我的小猫吗？”
The favor is, would you mind watching my poisonous pets?
这个忙就是，你介意帮我照看一下我的有毒宠物吗？
Right.
好的。
All right.
So would you mind it?
那么你介意吗？
But in the end, the person agreed.
但最后，那个人同意了。
So it works, right?
所以这招管用，对吧？
It does work.
确实管用。
So would you mind, so listeners, would you mind listening to today's dialogue one more
那么，听众们，你们介意再听一遍今天的对话吗？
time at its normal speed before we come back to you and talk more about renting an apartment?
在我们回来和你们聊更多关于租房的事情之前，以正常速度再听一遍？
Okay, that's fine.
好的，没问题。
Bye.
再见。
What happened?
发生什么事了？
That's it.
就这样了。
My lease is up.
我的租约到期了。
I have to move.
我得搬家了。
What?
什么？
Why?
为什么？
Can't you renew it?
你不能续租吗？
The owner apparently is selling this place to make way for the construction of a parking
房东显然是要卖掉这个地方，
lot.
为建停车场腾地方。
Well, I can help you pack.
嗯，我可以帮你打包。
We should start looking for a new place for you ASAP.
我们应该尽快开始给你找新地方。
I think I might move in with my parents for a couple of months until I can find something.
我想我可能会搬去和父母住几个月，直到找到合适的房子。
You know how hard it is to find a decent place around here.
你知道在这附近找个像样的地方有多难。
I'm going to have to put most of my stuff in storage for a while.
我得把大部分东西暂时存进仓库。
Well, let me know if there's anything I can do to help out.
好吧，如果有什么我能帮忙的，告诉我。
Actually, would you mind looking after my pet tarantula and snake for a couple of weeks?
其实，你介意帮我照看我的宠物狼蛛和蛇几个星期吗？
Sure.
当然可以。
All right, so moving in.
好的，那么说到搬家。
Now, you have different stages in your life, right?
现在，你人生中有不同阶段，对吧？
When you move out, for example, you move out of your parents' home and you live on your
比如，当你搬出去时，你离开父母家自己住，
own and then maybe, like in this case, you would move back in with your parents.
然后可能像这种情况，你会搬回父母家。
How do you see that happening?
你怎么看待这种情况？
I see it very often.
我经常看到这种情况。
My brother just moved back in with my parents.
我哥哥刚搬回我父母家。
Really?
真的吗？
Yeah, I think that it depends on the person, honestly.
是啊，我觉得这真的因人而异。
I mean, especially because the economy has really been suffering for the last year.
我是说，特别是因为过去一年经济一直很糟糕。
A lot of people are doing this because, you know, in a lot of cities in America, you can
很多人这么做是因为，你知道，在美国很多城市，
spend a thousand to two thousand dollars a month for an apartment to rent.
你每个月可能要花一千到两千美元租公寓。
And that's a small apartment or a shared apartment.
而且那还是小公寓或合租公寓。
And so I understand this is a really well, it's a better option now than it was before
所以我觉得这现在确实是个更好的选择，比以前好。
because everyone wants independence.
因为每个人都想要独立。
But sometimes you just can't afford it.
但有时候你就是负担不起。
Exactly.
没错。
And it's a cultural thing because some people move out of their parents' home, maybe for
这也是文化差异，因为有些人会搬出父母家，也许是为了
college.
上大学。
It's very common in the US for students to study in another city or another state.
在美国，学生去另一个城市或州读书很常见。
Right.
对。
And but then maybe coming back home and moving in with your parents or in other cultures,
但之后可能又会回家和父母住，或者在其他文化中，
maybe they don't move out at all.
也许他们根本不会搬出去。
Maybe they only move out once they're married.
也许他们只有结婚后才搬出去。
Exactly.
没错。
And a lot of people in China, I think in Shanghai specifically, don't move out until don't move
在中国，我觉得特别是在上海，很多人直到
out of their parents' home until they're going to get married.
结婚前都不会搬出父母家。
Right.
对。
And it does make sense in many big metropolises, because, as you say, rent is expensive.
在很多大都市这确实有道理，因为就像你说的，房租很贵。
Living on your own is expensive.
自己住很贵。
And, well, you don't have anyone to share those costs with like gas, water, electricity,
而且，你没有人和你分摊这些费用，比如煤气、水、电，
even food.
甚至食物。
Right.
对。
It's cheaper.
更便宜。
More people.
人多了。
And not to mention a little bit scary living on your own for the first time.
更别提第一次自己住还有点吓人。
It is a little bit scary.
是有点吓人。
What about having somebody move in with you, maybe a roommate or a girlfriend or boyfriend?
那找个人和你一起住呢，比如室友或女朋友/男朋友？
That's always the big step.
那总是个大步骤。
The big commitment.
重大的承诺。
You're in a relationship and you ask your partner to move in with you.
你谈恋爱了，然后让你的伴侣搬来和你一起住。
Yeah.
嗯。
The step before marriage, I guess.
我想是结婚前的一步。
Wow.
哇。
There's nothing before that?
那之前就没有别的步骤了吗？
Nothing before marriage?
结婚前没有别的步骤？
No.
没有。
That's pretty much it.
基本上就是这样。
You tell me.
你告诉我吧。
I don't know.
我不知道。
All right.
好吧。
That's all the time we have for today.
今天的时间就到这里。
But be sure to come to our website, EnglishPod.com.
但一定要来我们的网站 EnglishPod.com。
If you have any questions or any comments about this topic, we would be glad to have
如果你对这个话题有任何问题或评论，我们很乐意听取
your input on it.
你的意见。
And we'll see you guys there.
我们到时候见。
And if you have any suggestions for the step before the step before marriage, please let
如果你对结婚前一步的前一步有任何建议，请
us know because we're in the dark on this one.
告诉我们，因为我们对此一无所知。
So until next time.
那么下次见。
All right.
好的。
Stay safe everyone.
大家注意安全。